Alex Kisakye

Senior Cloud Engineer

Visa Status: Permanent Resident +61448172098 kisakye@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Broadly skilled Cloud Engineer who benefits from more than 12 years delivering scalable infrastructure services at an enterprise level. Serves as a technical SME on Unix/Linux and Linux-related scripting (Bash, Python, etc.). Experienced in the use of cloud native technologies (AWS & Azure) and open-source private clouds (Openstack, Opennebula, Cloudstack). A deep understanding of DevOps principles to serve as a bridge between Infrastructure and Developer teams, and leading implementation patterns to lower costs, improve speed to market, and increase efficiency. Strong experience with virtualisation, monitoring and automation (Puppet, Ansible, Packer, CloudFormation etc). Always proactive and works well under tight deadlines.

SKILLS

• Cloud Platforms AWS, Azure, Google Cloud, Openstack, Opennebula, Cloudstack, VMware, ProxMox

• Servers: Linux, Windows and Unix systems (virtualized and physical)

O/S: Oracle Solaris, UNIX/Linux [FreeBSD/CentOS/Redhat/Ubuntu], Windows Server

Databases: MySQL, Oracle, MSSQL and Elasticsearch engine

• Networking: VSAT, Cisco, HTTP(S), FTP, SMTP, POP, VoIP, DNS, VPN, IDS/IPS, 802.1X

• Languages: Python, PHP, Bash Scripting, PowerShell

• Automation Puppet, Ansible, Packer, CloudFormation, Terraform, Heat, Docker

• CI/CD Version Control Systems (GitHub, Gitlab, Bitbucket), Jenkins, JetBrains Stack

Monitoring
Zabbix, Grafana, Matomo, Nagios, Graylog

EXPERIENCE

F-Secure, South Africa - Linux Engineer

(Mar 2018 to Aug 2019)

Based out of Johannesburg, South Africa and serving as a technical subject matter expert on Linux engineering. The role forms part of a wider global team of up to 80 developers distributed in London, Johannesburg and Singapore. Reporting lines are to the Chief Product Officer who oversees global product activity.

- Provided technical engineering support needed to drive product development of Endpoint Detection and Response software; developed predominantly in Python and built for Linux, Windows and MacOSX operating systems.
- Reviewed infrastructure and proposed architecture changes (AWS & On-Premise) needed to support new features to market.
- Monitored infrastructure health and to ensure that infrastructure is functioning optimally and is

- able to deliver products and services to customers at low latency and high throughput.
- Reviewed new development features with Developers to drive the product life cycle.
- Worked with AWS (third-party) to ensure any degradation issues were resolved promptly, and liaised with IT (internal) on changes required to internal infrastructure to support traffic flow and deployments between environments.
- Installed Linux KVM hypervisor in the development environment to drive automated server provisioning processing, therefore reducing turnaround time from 3 to 5 days to just 3 minutes.
- Deployed puppet for configuration management of servers ensuring consistency of server builds.
- Moved project source code to Gitlab with DevOps functionality enabled there by improving code test, build, packaging process.
- Monitored build pipelines and worked with Developers on tweaks and/or modifications.

ThoughtWorks Inc, Australia & Africa Regions (Jun 2013 to Feb 2018)

- Technical Operations Lead
- Senior Cloud Engineer

Reported to the Head of Global IT Operations and responsible for IT infrastructure and operations for the Australian and African regions. Infrastructure is a mix of on-premise and cloud-based (AWS); and provides support to predominantly software developers and operations staff.

- Delivered a consistent and scalable infrastructure that was able to scale up with changes to operational and client service needs whilst leveraging from on-premise and AWS Cloud infrastructure.
- Built out and maintained DevOps infrastructure that allowed software engineers/developers to deploy solutions quickly.
- Updated and managed Cloud (AWS), VMWare & physical infrastructure used to support client project/software delivery including the build servers, build monitors, dev and test infrastructure.
- Project managed the setup of Sydney, NSW and Brisbane, QLD office infrastructure (phone, network, servers, physical security) to support about ~180 staff.
- Worked with client AWS CloudOps engineers to understand and explain the effect of product architecture decisions and how these decisions affect the distributed systems that drive enaineerina.
- Built internal Voice (VoIP) infrastructure that integrated with Cisco call manager in US, Brazil, India, and Australia.
- Drove automation through Puppet, CloudFormation, Terraform, Jenkins etc for client infrastructure.

Uganda Christian University, Uganda

(Jun 2006 to May 2013)

- IT Technical Manager
- Systems Administrator
- Helpdesk Specialist

Reported to both the ICT Director and the VP of Finance. The role of IT Technical Manager was responsible for supervising a team of staff to ensure IT operations and services meet service delivery needs for countrywide operations.

Managed IT infrastructure needs of 5 university campuses countrywide including budgeting,

- network and service delivery, road-mapping, project management, vendor contracting, risk management, and staff resourcing.
- Provided management weekly expense forecasting on recurring and fixed votes needed to strengthen the IT infrastructure and deliver next-generation services including Cloud and SaaS/laaS platforms.
- Deployed Microsoft Azure as the primary Cloud solution to meet current and future needs.
- Established an inter-campus IP-Sec VPN using Cisco equipment. This new network architecture improved system and resources sharing between the campuses while increasing security for data in transit.
- Introduced Intercampus VoIP and Video conferencing using available intercampus VPN drastically reducing costs spent on service providers.
- Increased the Fibre coverage on campuses from 25% to 70% and Increased the wireless coverage on the campuses to 100% using low cost Ubiquiti devices that saved the university \$380k vs Cisco wireless devices.

CERTIFICATIONS

- COA Certified Openstack Administrator
- ITIL Information Technology Infrastructure Library
- CEH Certified Ethical Hacker
- OSCP Offensive Security Certified Professional
- CCNA Certified Cisco Network Associate
- VoIP Voice Over Internet Protocol
- Network Operators Group Building Scalable Networks
- Cisco IT Essentials II

EDUCATION

- Msc. Computer Science Rhodes University, 2012
- Bsc. Information Technology Uganda Christian University, 2006

PUBLICATIONS

- An investigation into information security practices implemented by Research and Educational Network of Uganda (RENU) Member Institutions
- Security: A Necessary Piece of the Collaboration Puzzle